בוקר טוב Boker tov and welcome to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. We
are on
דף כב Daf Chaf Bet and we're going to start at the
bottom of 21. Yesterday we saw a משנה Mishnah on the bottom
of 20 and 21 that talks about rental and sale of property
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
whether it's houses or fields or bathhouses. We're picking up
three lines from the bottom of 21b with תניא. Tanya. רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר לא ישכיר אדם שדהו לכותי מפני שנקראת על שמו
וכותי זה עושה בו מלאכה בחולו של מועד.
Rabi Shimon ben Elazar omer lo yaskir adam sadehu lekuti mipne she-nikret
al shemo ve-kuti zeh
oseh bo melachah be-cholo shel mo'ed. So רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabi
Shimon ben Elazar says a person should not rent someone his field...
a person should not rent his field to
a כותי, kuti, to a Samaritan, because it still holds his name
and the owner's name, the Jew's name, and the כותי, kuti, now
our reasoning is that the כותי kuti might be doing מלאכה, melachah,
working it, in חול המועד, Chol HaMo'ed, twice a year, סוכות Sukkot
and פסח. Pesach. ואבל עובד כוכבים מאי שרי. Ve-aval oved kochavim mai
shari. But the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim we allow. This will sound
surprising to us and we'll see that the גמרא Gemara is asking
exactly the same question. דאמרי אריסא אריסותיה עביד. De-amri arisa arisuteh avid.
We think about the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim that I
guess in those days, maybe in our days too, they could tell
the difference, right, who is who? So people would know that the
עובד כוכבים oved kochavim is an אריס, aris, is a sharecropper, like,
works in the field, but the כותי, kuti, so you say אי
הכי נמי אמרי אריסא אריסותיה עביד. i hachi nami amri arisa arisuteh
avid. I have to breathe from the driving. אי הכי כותי נמי
אמרי אריסא אריסותיה עביד. I hachi kuti nami amri arisa arisuteh avid.
We can say about the כותי kuti the same thing. Why aren't
we thinking about the כותי kuti that he is also an אריס
aris and we're only thinking this about the
עובד כוכבים? oved kochavim? We think that the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
is obvious and the כותי kuti is going to be less obvious.
אי הכי מאי איריא מפני שנקראת על שמו? I hachi mai irya
mipne she-nikret al shemo? So we have the issue of the field
being called, right, having the person's name. And רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabi Shimon ben Elazar specifically said that the prohibition is
because of that, because of the name. But we can see that
we have two issues and we saw it in a little bit...
we saw it in previous discussions, we have the issue of לפני
עיוור לא תתן מכשול, lifnei iver lo titein michshol, right, that we
shouldn't fail somebody, right, put something in front of another person that
they could fail by. And here we have another reason משום שנקראת
על שמו, mishum she-nikret al shemo, because it carries the Jew's name.
And we'll see that the גמרא Gemara accepts both. It says תיפוק
ליה משום tipok lei mishum because of ויקרא Vayikra in פרשת קדושים
Parshat Kedoshim יט יד Yud Tet Yud Daled לפני עיוור לא תתן
מכשול, lifnei iver lo titein michshol,
that's what it should be. It says חדא ועוד קאמר חדא משום
לפני עיוור ועוד מפני שנקראת על שמו.
chada ve-od ka-amar chada
mishum lifnei iver ve-od mipne she-nikret al shemo. Both reasons are both
sources are places where we can derive this הלכה halachah
of not renting the field to somebody else. And I actually brought
a רמב"ם Rambam that deals with it. Interested in how we do
our job, because this is also specifically for שבת, Shabbat, and
the
thought might be somebody will see these people working in the field,
we will think that it's that now the Jew sent somebody to
be working on שבת, Shabbat, and that's problematic, all the אמירה לגוי.
amirah le-goy. Are we interested in seeing what רמב"ם Rambam has to
say about this as far as הלכה? halachah? רגע רגע, Rega rega,
I took a picture of the screen, hopefully I can read it.
Okay, לפיכך הפוסק עם עובד כוכבים לבנות לו חצרו או כותלו או
לקצור את שדהו או ששכרו שנה או שנתיים לבנות לו חצר או
ליטע לו כרם.
Lefichach haposek im oved kochavim livnot lo chatzeiro o kotlo o liktzor
et sadehu o she-secharo shanah o shenatayim livnot lo chatzeir o
litta lo karem. So somebody who makes a deal with the non-Jew
to build a yard or a wall or cut the field or
hired him for a year or two to build him fix up
his yard or plant a vineyard. או לקצור את שדהו או ששכרו
שנה ושנתיים לבנות לו החצר או ליטע לו כרם. o liktzor et
sadehu o sheschoro shana ushnataim livnot lo hachazer o lita lo karem.
So somebody who makes a deal with the non-Jew to build a
yard or a wall or cut the field or hired him for
a year or two to build him, fix up his yard or
give him a plant a vineyard, אם הייתה מלאכה במדינה או בתוך
התחום אסור לו להניחן לעשות בשבת. im hayta melacha bamedina o betoch
hatchum asur lo lehannichan laasot beshabbat. If this מלאכה melacha is inside
a place where people know that the Jew is not supposed to
be working on שבת, Shabbat, then he can't do it on שבת
Shabbat מפני הרואים שאינם יודעים שפסק. mipnei haroim sheeinam yodeim shepasak.
The people that will see it don't know what kind of an
arrangement they made and we deal with it a lot on our
when we're learning שבת. Shabbat. And so it will be מראית עין
marit ayin as if the Jew told the non-Jew to work for
him on שבת. Shabbat. But, says רמב"ם, Rambam, ואם הייתה המלאכה חוץ
לתחום מותר. veim hayta hamelacha chutz latchum mutar. If it's in a
place where people don't see it, מחוץ לתחום מותר, michutz latchum mutar,
שאין שם ישראל שיראה את הפועלים שעושים את המלאכה בשבת. sheein sham
Yisrael sheyireh et hapoalim sheosim et hamelacha beshabbat. There's no one there
that can see, right? So then that's a different arrangement. And one
more.
But what's the difference between the fields and your house? Yes.
Or or like if your house is in the middle of nowhere.
Okay. And then, so this is all,
whatever. Yes. We deal with it in הלכה, Halacha, where exactly are
the lines. וכן מותר לאדם להשכיר כרמו או שדהו לנוכרי. vechen mutar
leadam lehaskir karmo o sadehu lenochri. You can lease the vineyard or
the field to a non-Jew, אף על פי שהוא זורען ונוטען בשבת,
af al pi shehu zoran venotan beshabbat, even though he will seed
and plant on שבת. Shabbat. שהרואה יודע ששכורים הן או באריסות נתנם
להם. sheharo'eh yode'a sheschurim hen o bearisut netanam lahem.
That the person that sees knows that this field was rented out
and that it was given as a sharecropper. ודבר ששם ישראל בעליו
קרוי עליו ואין דרך רוב אנשי אותו המקום להשכירו או ליתנו באריסות
אסור להשכירו לנוכרי. vedavar sheshem Yisrael baalav karui alav veein derech rov
anshei oto hamakom lehaskiro o litno bearisut asur lehaskiro lenochri. This is
our reading רמב"ם Rambam related to the דף. daf.
Something that it has a Jewish name and most people,
it's not their way to rent it or lease it or give
it as a sharecropper, that is not allowed to rent to a
non-Jew מפני שהנוכרי עושה באותו המקום מלאכה בשבת והוא נקרא על שם
ישראל בעליו mipnei shehanochri oseh beoto hamakom melacha beshabbat vehu nikra al
shem Yisrael baalav because the non-Jew will do work on שבת, Shabbat,
but it still carries the name of the non-Jew. And now we
have... of the Jew. Carries the name of the Jew while somebody
else is doing the job. And now we have a little bit
of a case. Not quite a story but a case. הינהו מוריקאי
דעובד כוכבים נקיט בשבתא וישראל בחד בשבתא. hinhu morikai deoved kochavim nakit
beshabta veYisrael bechad beshabta.
So we have a field, it's a field of saffron, of כרכום,
karkom, and the
עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, one second, the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim and
the Jew are working it together. דעובד כוכבים נקיט בשבתא. deoved kochavim
nakit beshabta. We're כ"ב kaf-bet a few lines from the top. And
ישראל Yisrael on חד בשבתא, chad beshabta, on a Sunday. אתו לקמיה
דרבא שרא להו. atu lekamei deRava shara lehu. They went in front
of רבא Rava and he allowed them to make this deal. איתיביה
רבינא לרבא. eitiveih Ravina leRava.
So רבינא Ravina challenged רבא Rava allowing them to make this deal.
And he brings them
a ברייתא. braita. ישראל ועובד כוכבים שקיבלו שדה בשותפות לא יאמר ישראל
לעובד כוכבים טול חלקך בשבת ואני בחול. Yisrael veoved kochavim shekiblu sade
beshutfut lo yomar Yisrael leoved kochavim tol chelkecha beshabbat vaani bechol. So
a
non-Jew and a Jew that have a field together, a Jew can't
say to the non-Jew, "You take the share of שבת Shabbat and
I take my share of the rest of the week." But then,
ואם התנו מתחילה מותר. veim hitnu mitechila mutar. If this was decided
in advance, it's okay. ואם באו לחשבון, veim bau lecheshbon,
if they calculated it later, then it's not allowed. Look at רש"י
Rashi on the right side with both things.
ואם באו לחשבון veim bau lecheshbon and also אסור. asur.
אסור, asur, you can see the שכר, sechar, שכר שבת הוא
נוטל.
sechar Shabbat hu
notel. דגלי דעתיה דעובד כוכבים שלוחו הויה. degali daateih deoved kochavim shelucho
havaya. This would mean that the Jew takes the wages of שבת
Shabbat and it's obvious that he sent the non-Jew to do his
work on שבת Shabbat and therefore not allowed.
So when רבינא Ravina said this to רבא, Rava, reminded him of
this ברייתא, braita, it said איכסיף, ichsif, רבא Rava was embarrassed. רבינא
Ravina reminded him that really he shouldn't have permitted these קורקם kurkum
field sharers to create
this
kind of thing. But then לסוף איגלאי מילתא דהתנו מעיקרא הוו. lesof
iglay milta d'hitnu me'ikara havo. Later it was revealed
that they really had the deal from the beginning in advance, and
that there was an arrangement, and therefore רבא Rava did rule correctly.
Okay. רב גביה מבי כתיל Rav Geviha miBe Katil אמר, amar, he
remembers this story or a likewise story differently. אמר, amar, הנהו שתלי
דערלה הוו. hanehu shtilei d'orla havo. This is not a saffron field,
this was really ערלה orla plants.
Again we have a רש"י Rashi on this: ישראל ועובד כוכבים קיבלו
שדה בשותפות ונטעה ויטלו
החצי בין שניהם ונתעסק עובד כוכבים כל צרכו שני ערלה ואכלן וישראל
קיבל שלוש שנים אחרות כנגדן ואכלן.
Yisrael v'oved kochavim kiblu sadeh b'shutafo v'neta'ah v'yitlu
hachatzi bein shneihem v'nita'sek oved kochavim kol tzorko shnei orla v'achlan v'Yisrael
kibel shalosh shanim acherot k'negdan v'achlan. So in the field, right, we
have six years in the cycle, the first three years of the
ערלה, orla, the non-Jew was working the field and ate whatever he
ate, and ישראל, Yisrael, the Jew, received the three years afterwards and
ate those. Okay.
And the גמרא Gemara tells us: עובד כוכבים אכיל שני דערלה וישראל
שני דהיתירא.
oved kochavim achil shnei d'orla
v'Yisrael shnei d'heteira. אתו לקמיה דרבא שרי להו. atu l'kamei d'Rava sharei
lehu. Also in this situation, when they went in front of רבא,
Rava, he allowed them. So what, is the situation really comparable?
Is it really the same, the field
as it is with שבת? Shabbat? And we'll see that it is
not because there is no, there's no
issue
with the Jew working the field or sharing the field in this
kind of way.
Okay. והא אותיביה רבינא לרבא. veha otivieh Ravina l'Rava. But wait, if
this is, is this helping רבא Rava or is this not helping
רבא? Rava? What did רבינא Ravina come to do with this example?
And the גמרא Gemara decides לסיועי סייעיה. lesiyu'ei say'eih. It came, רבינא
Ravina wanted to help רבא, Rava,
not object. והא כסיף. veha kasif. But we're saying that he was
embarrassed. גמרא Gemara says לא היו דברים מעולם. lo hayu devarim me'olam.
It was not, he was not,
this is not how the story went.
And the ערלה orla really proved the opposite, like that there are
situations that they can share because there's no prohibition on the Jew
to share the field in that kind of way. It's not the
same as on שבת. Shabbat. It doesn't say to the Jew don't
work the field, just can't eat the fruit. But if he shares
it with a non-Jew there's, there's not a problem.
The non-Jew can eat ערלה.
orla. It's מצוה או אונס? mitzvah o ones? Pardon? Yeah, it's מצוה
או אונס, mitzvah o ones, right?
Six years or so. Okay.
Okay, but now we see that we, we have an,
it's not the שביעית shvi'it in other words, it's the,
I mean, I think they bring the example because there is relevance,
but they reject it as helping the שבת, Shabbat, that it's not
the same.
But we'll see, we understand that they brought two examples that conflict
each other and they'll, they'll dismiss. בעו מיניה סתמא מאי? ba'u mineih
stama mai? תא שמע אם התנו מתחילה מותר. ta shema im hitnu
mitchila mutar. הא סתמא אסור. ha stama assur. So there's a, there's
a dilemma, right? If they did not specify that the non-Jew would
work on שבת, Shabbat,
and they also did not calculate the profit, right,
then what is the הלכה, halacha, מאי? mai? And it says
if they created this תנאי, tnai, this condition from the beginning, that
the non-Jew would have the share of the profit in exchange for
the work on שבת, Shabbat, right, while the Jew receives the rest
of the week, then it should be permitted. This means that without
the specification it's אסור. assur. So the סתמא stama is אסור, assur,
but the תנאי tnai from לכתחילה lechatchila
is
מותר. mutar. But wait, but like in the last thing we said,
if they calculate it is forbidden. We just had this statement here
that it said אסור. assur. אם באו לחשבון אסור. im ba'u l'cheshbon
assur. So if they came to calculate the profit, it's forbidden. That
would mean that the סתמא stama is allowed, that without specification is
permitted. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. ela
meha leka l'mishma mina. This is like we can't really find a
ראיה raya from this because we have two things that conflict each
other. And with that we finished, huh?
Like a תיקו? teiku?
It's like a תיקו teiku but they don't say תיקו. teiku. They
just like say we can't learn from him. הדרן עלך
לפני אידיהן. Hadran Alach Lifnei Ideihen. We say goodbye to the first
chapter with בסייעתא דשמיא b'siata d'shmaya start the second chapter with the
משנה. Mishnah. אין
מעמידין בהמה בפונדקאות של
עובדי כוכבים מפני שחשודים על הרביעה ולא תתייחד אשה עמהם מפני שחשודים
על העריות ולא יתייחד אדם עמהם מפני שחשודים על שפיכות דמים.
Ein maamidin behema befundekaot shel ovdei kochavim mipnei shechashudim al hareviah v'lo
tityached isha imahem mipnei shechashudim al
haarayot v'lo yityached adam imahem mipnei shechashudim al shefichut damim. So
the first thing is we have three things in this משנה Mishnah
and hopefully if we make it safely to the end of 22,
we'll be able to at least unpack the first statement. The first
one is that we do not leave an animal in the פונדק,
pundak, in the inn of עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, of an idolater,
because they're suspicious of רביעה, reviah, of mating with animals.
And second thing is that a woman should not be in ייחוד
yichud alone with them because they're suspicious of עריות, arayot, of immoral
relations. And a person should not be with them alone in general,
man or woman, because they're suspicious of
murder.
We should ask a few questions. We have a רש״י Rashi on
the פונדקאות fundekaot which we have a question on the רש״י Rashi
and we can solve that. I'm going to delete the ones we're
not dealing with today first. The second one should raise a question
because if it says a woman should not have ייחוד yichud with
them, so we also know that a woman should not have a
ייחוד yichud with a Jewish man. Like what is the exclusion, right,
that we make for the idolaters? Luckily not today's topic and we
will deal with it tomorrow.
רש״י Rashi on the פונדקאות fundekaot trying to explain says שעושים להתאכסן
עוברי דרכים שם ומעלים שכר לבעלים.
Sheosim l'hitachsen ovrei drachim sham
u'maalim sachar l'baalim. So, huh?
It's an inn where we pay. So why this specification of payment?
Well, because that's what you do.
Right, but like what if I come there for free? What if
somebody knows somebody?
If someone let you stay there for free. If you know them,
that might be a little bit different because like, you know, then
if you know them, you don't want to like, they're your friend,
you don't want to like, you know, take advantage of their animals.
The
at least the explanation that I
heard weeks or so later is that in the situation where there
is no payment,
there might be like a, oh well, you're not paying so I
might, whatever, use your animal or something like that. But even in
a place where there is payment, right, כל שכן, kal v'chomer, yeah,
it should be that it's
not
allowed and we don't put the animal there.
I always thought that was meant to contrast with the Jews or
you know, your neighbor, you know,
since he knows you, you know, you wouldn't be
like, it wouldn't be likely to be. Yeah, okay. We will see.
This is going to be, I don't
know,
unpopular page because the whole page is about bestiality and different... We
had it before. We had it on דף טו עמוד א.
daf tet-vav amud aleph.
We did, but there we had בהמה דקה. behema daka. I was
so lucky to have בהמה דקה. behema daka.
Yeah, I know. So there we differentiated between the בהמה דקה behema
daka and the בהמה גסה behema gassa and we talked about sale.
And now we're talking about...
But we recorded this, we recorded this.
In the גמרא. Gemara. Yes,
we did. They quoted back and forth from 14 to 22 and
from 22 back to 14.
Lucky. There's a note here in what the תוספות Tosafot say in
his time this...
Yes, yes, yes. We can look at this. No, it's right there
in the bottom.
I need glasses for the תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, והתניא בגמרא אין מוסרים
בהמה לרועה שלהם ויש ליתן טעם על מה אנחנו סומכים לייחד בהמותינו
עמהם ואף אנו מוסרים בהמותינו לרועה שלהם. V'hatanya b'gemara ein mosrim behema
l'roeh shelahem v'yesh liten taam al ma anachnu somchim l'yached behomoteinu imahem
v'af anu mosrim behomoteinu l'roeh shelahem. So they don't do what the
משנה Mishnah says. So
exactly. And we'll see that the גמרא Gemara also doesn't do what
the משנה Mishnah says and it's going to deal with how, how
come we don't? Okay, so I can, I can do it in
the Talmudic story and tell you the end so that you know
where we're going to so that the suspense is not so high
and we can just focus on the flow of the conversation.
And he's denoting here continuously about why
in
15a.
But I'd go with like an academic answer to answer a question
as opposed to, you know, what the historical reality was. I don't
know.
I'm actually
on
the side that's convinced that there was a lot of truth to
it. So don't shoot...
There was a lot of what?
Truth.
To bestiality. One, the Torah wouldn't speak about, like the Torah doesn't
say whatever, don't populate Mars or something. It doesn't talk about things
that were not an issue.
Well, the Torah didn't say anything about about this either. At least
the תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav didn't. You know, the תורה שבעל פה
Torah Shebe'al Peh is saying about it. Where's it say... where does
Torah say anything about like the non-Jews were always copulating...
you
know, it talks about an
איסור, Issur, but no one says that's not Jews.
Because they didn't know about Mars at the time. Who knows? You
know, like, maybe they didn't know of Mars, maybe they would have
said don't populate Mars. I don't know. You know, like, you can't
answer that. You know what I mean? It also, also, you know,
according to other שיטות, shittas, don't eat any שקצים, shkatzim, you know,
say 'Oh, but people don't want to eat those anyway,' right?
You know, but people do eat them.
No, but then they're two different opinions, right? There's, you know, you
can't eat the creepy crawly things. Right? But then but then one
of the opinions is no one eats them anyway, so why did
it even bother to say it? To give you שכר s'char for
not eating it. So you could say the same thing. Right? Yeah,
no, but I think, yeah, no, go on.
When it's
not...
when it's not a suspicion then it's not applicable, but it's just
saying...
Wait, wait, wait, we'll get there. We'll get there. Okay, so this
is, there's two problems. One is we have what we're going to
bring right now, a ברייתא, Baraita, תוספתא, Tosefta, that objects what the
משנה Mishnah is saying. Okay, so we're going to have to deal
with this contradiction, the תוספות Tosfot contradiction, and the fact that we
do take בהמה behemah from their בהמות. behemot. Okay, so how do
we, how do we settle both these things? But the fact, I,
like, maybe
maybe this should be an offline conversation, but I also like, and
maybe, you know, maybe again this is a bias, but like growing
up in Israel, it was a thing that people would talk about,
about shepherds, whatever.
As a joke? For real?
Look, I've never seen anyone do it so I can't talk from
מראה עין, mar'eh ayin, but it was not like 'Oh, wow, this
is such a big deal.' It was like 'Yeah, this is what's
going
on.' Mean Jewish shepherds? There were no Jewish shepherds, but now this
would be an interesting conversation because now there are Jewish shepherds. Yes.
Yes.
Historically or like in rock art and stuff like that in prehistoric
times, right? But I feel like there's some connotation, of religious connotation
of like gods that are half-animal and god... like, I don't know
that it's the mention
of it
actually happening or because this was like some imagined idea of how
you got gods that were half-animal. Right? Like myths of humans and
animals and...
So that was a possibility? Are you like on the רבינא Ravina
side or on the... No, no, no, like on the תיובא tiyuva
or like in a way that it would be in the collective
consciousness and therefore something that
people could think about
the like prohibit, but that wasn't actually like happening on a regular
basis. It was more like this like
something that they could perceive of because there were results to those
unions, kind of?
Right? Yes. Yeah. Or if the mythology has a like half-human half-animals
then there must be a way that that happened and so there
needs to be like an imagination.
I also think like we, in some ways we live like in,
whatever, a very cleaned-up society, right? So like this does not, we
don't think that that's what people would do. But yet, there's a
whole industry that goes around let's say sex toys, etc., that you
know, imagine if somebody found this 2,000 years ago and they'd be
like, oh, people are having sex with plastic. You'll be like, this
is like crazy.
It is crazy!
I mean, I feel like we don't live in that cleaned-up of
a society. Okay. I mean some of the proclivities that people have
today... Yes.
They take it out in a slightly different way.
So they use plastic instead of animals. You know?
But some of them are called animals.
I don't think there's bestiality as much as people... I could be
wrong. I think that's not something that's
actually many people would have the proclivity today. I would guess that
they probably didn't back then either.
Maybe. We don't know, but we have a whole page to entertain
ourselves with this
for the next half hour, so just sit tight and let's see
if we can go through with it. Yeah, put your seatbelts on
because it's going to be a little... I can't even say bumpy,
but okay. All right. ורמינהו. U'reminhu. Yeah, put your seat belts on
because it's going to be a little bit, I can't even say
bumpy, but okay. Alright. ורמינהו. U'reminhu. So the גמרא Gemara raises a
problem to this משנה, Mishnah, because the משנה Mishnah says, right, אין
מעמידין בהמה בפונדקאות ein ma'amidin behemah bifundeka'ot של עובדי כוכבים shel ovdei
kochavim מפני שחשודים על הרביעה. mipnei she'chashudim al ha'revi'ah. We're worried that
the non-Jews will engage in bestiality and so we don't park our
animals in their פונדק. pundak. The objection is that we
know, don't park our animals like the ancient version of the car.
Yeah, it was, in some ways it was. Also you rent it
like you rent a room. Right right. Okay. We'll try to stick
to the text. Don't pick up your eyes from the thing. Okay.
So the objection is that we know, we have a teaching, לוקחים
מהם בהמה לקורבן lokchim meihem behemah l'korban ואין חוששין v'ein chosheshin לא
משום רובע ולא משום נרבע lo mishum rovei v'lo mishum nirba לא
משום מוקצה ולא משום נעבד. lo mishum muktzeh v'lo mishum ne'evad. So
we know, we have a teaching that we can purchase an animal
from a non-Jew for the use for a קורבן. korban. For a
קורבן korban the animal should have
been had nothing done to it, and we purchase this animal without
any concern that
maybe it had relations or maybe it was the object of bestiality
or maybe it was מוקצה, muktzeh, it was set aside for idolaters'
worship, or that it was already worshipped, נעבד. ne'evad.
So now we're going to take this דף daf to try to
settle the contradiction.
Contradiction is clear, right? משנה Mishnah says don't don't put it
and the גמרא Gemara says we do take.
The פסוק, pasuk, let me just close this, the פסוק pasuk that
the גמרא Gemara is relying on and we will see that it
addresses it is in ויקרא Vayikra
first chapter
verse two, א-ב, aleph-bet,
אדם כי יקריב מכם קורבן להשם מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן
תקריבו. Adam ki yakriv mikem korban l'Hashem min ha'behemah min ha'bakar u'min
ha'tzon takrivu. So you can take from the בהמה, behemah, from the
בקר, bakar, and from the צאן. tzon. Okay.
So how how do we put these two together?
We see that the פסוק pasuk says from, take from, and there's
an understanding that there is an exclusion there. Don't take everybody, the
ones that were harmed in any way don't take them, but you
can take from them. So that means that we don't suspect all
the animals of all the non-Jews of having been subjected to bestiality.
How do we work this out? Okay. בשלמא מוקצה ונעבד אי מאי
דאקדשיה אי מאי דסגדיה לא הוי מזבני ליה. Bishlama muktzeh v'ne'evad ei
mai d'akdishei ei mai d'sagdeih la havei mzavni lei. So those that
are מוקצה muktzeh and נעבד, ne'evad, those that were set aside for
idol worship or have been worshipped, right, if they were set aside
and if they are there for idol worship, the non-Jew would not
sell it to you anyway because that's what they're out there for,
so we don't have to worry about. אלא רובע ונרבע לחוש? Ela
rovei v'nirba lachush? So should we worry about the bestiality
variations? אמר רב תחליפא אמר רב שילא בר אבינא משמיה דרב עובד
כוכבים חס על בהמתו שלא תעקר. Amar Rav Tachlifa amar Rav Shila
bar Avina mishmei d'Rav oved kochavim chas al behemto shelo te'aker. So
there
is a general understanding that the non-Jew חס, chas, like feels for
his animal, and especially is worried about her שלא תעקר, shelo te'aker,
so it will not become barren. How does bestiality cause barrenness is
not completely clear to me, but there is one reference later on
to if a male animal has relations with a woman human,
that it creates an attraction between the animal and the person that
kind of makes the animal dependent on the human in a different
way. So they don't refer to it here because that animal is
a male.
Suggested here that if a female animal is sodomized by a man,
its reproductive organs
suffer damage irreparably. Right right right.
Because תעקר, te'aker, because he worried that it's...
so let's see how we're going to do this. We have Ach...
lucky 13 or something.
We have male.
Okay, so how are we going to do this? This is human...
oh we don't want pictures. This is going to get complicated. Alright.
We have the animal, okay, so we have male and male and
my teacher is doing קידושין kiddushin
right now, so male and female, female and male, and female and
female.
What?
Oh don't look.
It's okay. Symbols like an animal. Huh? Symbols like an animal.
I think Rav Levi is just gonna
like finding it on the board tomorrow morning so he can remind
us how glad he is
that he is not here for this now. Exactly.
Later on today, yeah,
okay,
okay, back to the text. So the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim is
like does not want his animal to become barren so and because
this is the teaching that the bestiality will cause it, so he
will not use it for that. Okay, so that explains התינח נקבות.
hatinach nekevot. So that explains why a human male will not want
to use his female animal because, right, because it's gonna make her
barren. זכרים מאי איכא למימר? secharim mai ika lemeimar? What are we
going to say about the males in this situation? אמר רב כהנא
amar Rav Kahana הואיל ומכחישין בבשר. hoeil umakhkhishin bivasar. So
something
happens to these animals that they like deteriorate. They become
skinny or like physically weaker. Again, what is
the... God forbid, process, but something happens to these animals that it's
not just that it's not good for us, like for humans to
be engaged in these kind of relationships, it's harmful for the animals.
אלא הא דתניא ella ha detanya but okay, לוקחין בהמה מרועה שלהם.
lokhkhin behemah meroeh shelahem.
We have a challenge that we're taught in a ברייתא baraita that
one can purchase an animal from their shepherds. לחוש דילמא
רבעה? likhush dilma reva'ah?
Shouldn't we worry that maybe there was a רביעה? revi'ah?
And the answer is רועה שלהם יתיירא משום הפסד שכרו. roeh shelahem
yitayre mishum hefsed sekharo. And the shepherd worries because there's gonna be
loss of a financial loss and specifically for himself on the job.
If we understand that the animal diminishes from being engaged in this
activity, then the shepherd worries that his flock diminishes. So yeah.
The point of the previous one was that meaning that's why we
don't worry about buying from them because they're not going to do
it to their own animals but we still worry about putting our
animals with their
shepherds because their shepherds are in an inn or whatever right because
they're not going to care about hurting our animals.
In fact you'll see not to be a spoiler but they're especially
attracted to our animals. Oh.
Okay. But we also have a teaching אלא הא דתניא ella ha
detanya אין מוסרין בהמה לרועה שלהם
ein mosrin behemah ler'oeh
shelahem למה? lama? So how do we explain this? רועה שלהם יתיירא
משום הפסד שכרו. roeh shelahem yitayre mishum hefsed sekharo. He's worried one,
two financial concerns the shepherd has. One is that the animal loses
its value, right, that was the concern of the owner and the
flock diminishing, but also the shepherd is worried that he's not going
to get paid if the owner sees that that's what happens to
his animals, right, if the animals diminish.
Okay.
Buying something from them, but it's saying you don't want to also
leave our animals there.
Yes. לוקחין בהמה מרועה שלהם. lokhkhin behemah meroeh shelahem.
Should we worry? Okay again, not to spoil this, but we'll see
in the very end that there is a sort of a בדיעבד
bediavad and this is how they resolve the two contradictions.
That מלכתחילה milekhatkhila we would worry, but if we come to a
sale and now we're looking at this particular animal, chances are that
it wasn't subject to bestiality and that it's okay. And this is
how we're going to juggle those two statements. One is don't do
it and the other one is we take from their animals. So
this is we're going to figure it out. out that in the
good Jewish fashion, the answer to the two contradictions is yes and
that we can do both. Okay. אינהו דידעי בהדדי מרתתי, אנן דלא
ידעינן בהו לא מרתתי. Inhu diydei bahadadei mirteti, anan d'la yadinan behu
lo mirteti.
The shepherd, and this is a little bit of a digression to
the specific issue of the shepherd,
the non-Jews, they're aware of each other's practices and so they would
know what's going on. We don't know what this looks like. Like
if we give an animal and something happened to it, we might
be like, oh, it ate something bad or it has a virus
or whatever. We would not suspect that there was bestiality. So we
don't know to identify the signs of an animal being subject to
this kind of thing, which means the shepherd or shepherd is afraid
when he's among his own like people and less afraid vis-a-vis us.
Yes. Vis-a-vis so prevalent you would think that the Rabbis would just
like they when they are studying all these minute details, you know
when they're doing שחיטה shechita or something. If it was very prevalent
at the time, you would think the Rabbis would also know how
to identify.
Like a physical sign you know once you slaughter the animal?
No, I'm just setting... I'm just saying that they were very aware
in their own society of minute details of different situations. You would
think they would also be able to identify that, learn it from,
you know what I'm saying?
It's a little bit of a yes and no.
I'm just suggesting.
I don't know how far to take this. Like
no, people, we can't compare exactly, but like people in abuse situations,
so sometimes you have whatever kids that went through some form of
abuse and they're like, oh, he's disruptive, maybe he needs a different
curriculum, maybe he blah blah blah blah blah. When somebody else might
look at it and be like, they went through a trauma. So
somebody that can identify it maybe can see it better and somebody
that doesn't know what's going on
doesn't see it in the same way. And maybe this example is
bad so just throw it away. But here is what רבא Rava
tells us. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: היינו דאמרי אינשי. Hainu d'amri inshi.
This is what people say. We looked it up. מכתבא גלי ליה
בזא, רגלא בחבריה ידע. Machtava glei lei b'za, ragla b'chavreiah yada. Like
it's an expression which means that the
marble is worried about the etching tool. And רגלא בחבריה ידע ragla
b'chavreiah yada like the the people that hang around with each other
know each other's mannerism. If when we're not connected to something, we
don't see it. And it's complex but there's some truth to it,
right? We know things that we know and I guess in English
they say it takes one to know one, right? Like you have
to be on the in in order to know what's going on
and when you're not it's harder to identify exactly the issue.
Okay. Now with that,
we've managed to sort of explain both these things. One is the
male with the female because of אקרות, akarut, right? And this is
because הכחש? hekchesh? Like it becomes skinny, ill, physically unfit and so
therefore we're not worried because the non-Jew feels bad for his animal
and therefore when the גמרא Gemara says that we can take מן
הבהמה, min habehema,
it's okay. We're worried that it could happen but likely it didn't
happen. Okay. אי הכי זכרים, Ei hachi zacharim, this is good.
So let's not
wait a second. So אי הכי זכרים מנקבות לא נזבון דחיישינן דלמא
מרבעא ליה עילויה. ei hachi zacharim mi'nekevot lo nizbun d'chaishinan dilma marba
lei ilaveiah.
So the now we have an issue of a woman owning a
male animal. Okay.
Okay.
So now we're also concerned of purchasing male animals from females.
מנקבות לא נזבון, mi'nekevot lo nizbun, we're not purchasing animals from female
owners.
And we're concerned, why are we concerned? דחיישינן דלמא מרבעא ליה עילויה,
d'chaishinan dilma marba lei
ilaveiah, כיוון דמיקריא
מרתתא. keivan d'mikria mirteta. The
if she was engaged in bestiality, the woman... The animal would
develop certain attachment to this woman which will like tell by
default on the woman on what she did. And therefore like create
whatever and embarrassment or an uncomfortable situation and therefore we assume maybe
she wouldn't do it because it's you can't hide it. Okay, but
here we have a teaching which will make everybody happy, heads up.
אלא הא דתני רב יוסף Ela ha d'tani Rav Yosef but we
also if we're not worried, right, okay, if we're not worried because
the animal like discloses, right, the woman's transgression, but we have a
teaching by רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אלמנתא לא תרבי כלבא Almanta lo
tarbi kalba
a widow should not raise a dog, a male dog, כלבא kalba
not כלבתא. kalbata. ולא תשרי בר בי רב באושפיזא V'lo tashrei bar
beirav b'ushpiza and she shouldn't be allowed to have a single like
Yeshiva student, בר בי רב, bar beirav, as a host as a
not host, hosted, as somebody who's lodging in her place. Okay, בשלמא
בר בי רב צניע לה. Bishlama bar beirav tznie lah.
So granted,
makes sense to not allow her to have a male student in
her home
because there's a issue of צניעות, tzniut, right?
And
let's see,
okay, because there's an issue of צניעות tzniut with the male, there's
also an issue of because it's צניעות tzniut for him, for the
Yeshiva guy who's now living at the widow's house, because it's צניעות
tzniut for him, if something happened between them, he will not tell,
right? Because like he's a person. But the dog, אלא כלבא כיוון
דמיגרי בה מרתתא. ela kalba kevan d'migri bah mirtata. The dog because
it is like aroused by this woman now, then she's afraid because
everybody will everybody will know that she has a relationship. Therefore because
of the fear, the fear will deter her from doing it, therefore
she should be permitted to have a dog. And also there is
an explanation כיוון דכי שדיא ליה אומצא ומשריך בתרה מימר אמרי אינשי
היינו דמשריך בתרה משום אומצא דקמשריך.
kevan d'ki shadya lei umtza
u'mashrich batra meimar amri inshi hai d'mashrich batra mishum umtza d'kamashrich. Okay,
so she could always say
or we can assume that the dog follows her because she throws
him a אומצא umtza or still a modern word like a juicy
piece of meat. So when the dog develops this behavior of משריך
mashrich of like dragging behind her,
it can be attributed to the meat that she feeds it and
not because of the relationship that they have. It's interesting that
they isolate the dog because apparently dogs and dogs behave
differently to people that feed them than let's say sheep. Sheep or
a cows they're happy to see their food coming but they don't
like walk after them they don't have this like dragging behind them.
Okay, great. So we're also not worried about this situation, right, because
we can hang it on the meat that she's feeding him. Great.
Okay, so great. Last thing, נקבות אצל נקבות מאי טעמא לא מייחדינן?
Nekeivot etzel nekeivot mai ta'ama lo miyachdinan? Why, okay,
so now this is last option. Why don't we allow female animals
with female owners, right, because we can't worry about any of these
situations? אמר מר עוקבא בר חמא מפני שהעובדי כוכבים מצויין אצל נשי
חבריהן ופעמים שאינו מוצאה ומוצא את הבהמה ורובעה.
Amar Mar Ukva bar Chama mipnei sheha'ovdei kochavim metzuyin etzel neshei chavreihen
u'fiamim she'eino
motzah u'motzei et habehema v'rova.
So the explanation is the joyful explanation is sometimes the עובד
כוכבים, ovad kochavim, I don't want to use non-Jewish actually,
the idolater, like he hangs around at his friend's wife's place.
And sometimes he doesn't find the wife at home but he finds
the animal and so he will have sex with the animal. ואיבעית
אימא אפילו מוצאה נמי רובעה. V'iba'it eima afilu motzah nami rova.
Even if he finds the wife, he's so excited he gets two
for the price of one, he will. also be רובע rova the
animal.
דאמר מר חביבה עליהן בהמתן של ישראל יותר מנשותיהן. de'amar mar chaviva
aleihen behemtan shel Yisrael yoteir mi-neshoteihen.
The animals of Israel
are more attractive than their own wives.
Okay. Huh?
I said lovely. Yes, lovely.
Okay, now what is the explanation that they're
that, you know, whatever, for this whole complexity here? דאמר רבי יוחנן.
de'amar Rabbi Yochanan. Huh?
We knew it was getting to that.
We knew it was getting to that and whatever, let's see if
we can survive it. דאמר רבי יוחנן, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan, בשעה שבא
נחש על חוה הטיל בה זוהמא. besha-ah she-ba nachash al Chava hitil
bah zohama. When the נחש, nachash, well, it literally says came
upon חוה, Chava,
at the time of them being in the garden, it put something
contaminated in her. Ask a question about this.
What? Did you guys just lose your mind? Where do we have
any reference to the fact that the snake had relations? This is
what the גמרא Gemara just said, right? The גמרא Gemara said that
the snake had relations with חוה. Chava. Where do we have it?
So there's two like textual proofs.
One, חוה, Chava, and this is from other places in the גמרא
Gemara in
שבת קמ״ו, Shabbat kuf mem vav, רש״י Rashi says about the פסוק
pasuk in
בראשית, Bereishit, הנחש השיאני. ha-nachash hissi-ani. השיאני hissi-ani can be like the
נחש nachash tested me, right, like he whatever, diverted me. But נישואין
nisu-in is also marriage. And if it's spelled like with שין sin
and אלף, alef, it would be like the נחש, nachash, this is
what רש״י Rashi says,
the נחש nachash had some form of an engagement with חוה Chava
that resembles נישואין. nisu-in. What can that be? Obviously they were not
married. So this is one understanding. And the other understanding is that
at the end when God says to all of them, here the
תנ״ך Tanakh is there, okay,
when God says to all of them what they've done, then it
says to the נחש, nachash, יען כי עשית זאת, ya-an ki asita
zot, because you did this. What is this that the נחש nachash
possibly did? There's only one this, right? It's not like he whatever,
picked up a shirt he wasn't supposed to from Nordstrom or some
other little minority,
minutia, but that he had relations with חוה Chava and therefore to
all women,
I guess, don't listen, it's all right, therefore all women have like
some animalistic thing from this interaction according to the גמרא. Gemara.
And
even their offspring, so it'd be men as well, I would guess.
Yeah, looking at this note, it's just saying cast impurity into חוה
Chava causing her and her offspring to lust after the
but right now we're specifically in the women with women situation. Okay,
so but then we should say אי הכי ישראל נמי, ee hachi
Yisrael nami, we also are offspring of חוה. Chava. What is it
that we think we were relieved?
Yes, well I forgot what the word was.
השיאני, hissi-ani, הנחש השיאני. ha-nachash hissi-ani. It should be in
Chapter
3, at the end of גמל Gimmel when they have this whole
calculation.
גמל י״ג. Gimmel yud-gimmel.
Okay.
What is kind of the cure for ישראל Yisrael that they are
not subject to this animalistic whatever contamination? I'm trying to use my
words carefully but clearly we could sit on this for a long
time in order to figure out exactly what it says. The גמרא
Gemara says ישראל שעמדו על הר סיני פסקה זוהמתם, עובדי כוכבים שלא
עמדו על הר סיני לא פסקה זוהמתם. Yisrael she-amdu al har Sinai
paskah zohamatam, ovdei kokhavim she-lo amdu al har Sinai lo paskah zohamatam.
So and we have this in other places that סיני Sinai is
like
a whatever, counter-medicine to different problem, problems,
challenges, flaws, maybe flaws is better.
And therefore, yeah, סיני Sinai being a marriage, and when somebody gets
married their sins are forgiven and I don't know if this relates
to that.
Okay, or maybe like it cancels the previous marriage or something like
that.
I don't know but there is like in שיר השירים Shir HaShirim
one of the things they quote, in שיר השירים Shir HaShirim it
says, הנך יפה רעייתי ומום אין בך. hinach yafah ra-iyati umum ein
bakh. You are beautiful my friend and there is no flaw in
you. spouse, and there is no flaw in you. ומום אין בך.
Umumm ein bach. Nothing is wrong with you. So somewhere along the
way, something, I mean, if you think about it and again it's
another intense detour to go into, is this like the גמרא's Gemara
answer to original sin?
That we have a cure for it by being at סיני. Sinai.
But what about before סיני? Sinai? I mean, what does this say
about the generations...
Yes, yes, yes, the foremothers, right, and all the generations before סיני,
Sinai,
what about them?
You know, I can't answer the- I can't answer the whole thing,
but I take the גמרא Gemara like very seriously and I you
know try to unpack what they mean. I don't have all the
answers. That's I can state that clearly.
Clearly and proudly.
All right. So this now,
this now kind of resolves these issues.
Okay.
The four issues of combinations here. Guess where we're going to go
next.
If we're done with animals, with בהמות, Beheimot, what's left? Poultry. איבעיא
להו עופות. Iba'it lehu ofot. מאי תשמע? Mai tashma? Okay,
so are we worried about עופות? ofot? Because we also can take
certain עופות ofot for sacrifice.
Are we concerned that inappropriate
actions/bestiality was done with the עופות? ofot? מאי תש- מאי תשמע, Mai
tash- mai tashma, דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי חנינא: de'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Hanina: אני ראיתי. Ani ra'iti. I
have seen עובד כוכבים שלקח אווז מן השוק.
oved kochavim she'lakach avaz
min hashuk.
Close your eyes. I saw an idolater taking a goose from the
market, רבעה חנקה צלאה ואכלה. reva'ah, chanakah, tzl'ah, va'achalah.
He had engaged in bestiality with it, choked it, strangled
it, roasted it, and ate it.
Okay. ואמר
רבי ירמיה מדפתי:
Ve'amar
Rabbi Yirmiya mi-Difti:
אני
ראיתי, Ani ra'iti, like my father's bigger than your father, right? אני
ראיתי, Ani ra'iti, ערבי אחד שלקח ירך מן השוק וחקק בה כדי
רביעה רבעה צלאה ואכלה. Arvi echad she'lakach yarech min hashuk vechakak bah
kedei reviah, reva'ah, tzl'ah, va'achalah.
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says I saw something even worse. I saw
ערבי, Arvi, we don't- this is not like today's Arabs, there was
no Islam back then, but like ערבי Arvi from מעורב Me'urav like
mixed tribes that were in the area who took a thigh, a
piece of meat from the market. So this is now not a
goose that was alive, but a dead piece of meat and whatever
did whatever he did with it and then ate it.
No, the first one. The goose, yeah. The goose he choked, roasted
and ate. This is already dead and
ate
it. And then we should love רבינא Ravina who closes this discussion
until tomorrow. רבינא אמר לא קשיא. Ravina amar: La kashya. None
of
this is any problem. הא לכתחילה הא בדיעבד. Ha lechatchila, ha bedieved.
And this is the spoiler that I said from the beginning. This
is how we resolve the משנה Mishna with the גמרא. Gemara. Indeed
the גמרא Gemara brings us proofs that in every one of these
situations there's a reason that we can believe that the animal was
treated fairly whether the גוי Goy is חס chas or feeds it
or cares for it in any way. And therefore למעשה lema'aseh there
should not be a problem in us taking one of their animals
לקורבן lekurban like from בדיעבד. bedieved. בדיעבד, bedieved,
בדיעבד bedieved like you say this animal, this animal likely nothing happened
to it, but in the future I'm concerned.
You mean the meaning of בדיעבד bedieved
meaning you already bought the animal. Yeah, or like we're negotiating this
particular thing. Chances are it's okay, but in general I'm worried. Don't
worry, the same face you have, they have, and therefore they'll continue
some of this conversation and trying to explain it in the next
דף. daf.
Thank you for riding
with us this morning
on this crazy journey. Have a great day. Bye.